A Guide to the James J. Kilpatrick Papers 1950-1966
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
The James J. Kilpatrick Papers 1950-1966
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6626-b
35,680 items
This addition to the James J. Kilpatrick papers contains office files, 1950-1966, letters, speeches, articles, television debates, the Margaret Wagner file, and papers on Kilpatrick's books The Sovereign States, The Smut Peddlers, The Lasting South, and The Southern Case.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Library acquired these Papers from the author, n.d.
Scope and Content Information
The collection includes office files, 1950-1966, kept while Kilpatrick was editor of the Richmond News Leader, containing correspondence, unused editorials, speeches, articles, and scripts of television debates covering the major social and political issues from 1950 to 1966, especially race relations, politics, massive resistance, the doctrine of interposition, Virginia and national elections, the John Birch Society and its campaign to impeach Earl Warren, and the Catholic issue in the 1960 Presidential campaign.
Topics also include education, journalism, the Constitution, civil rights, conservatism, Douglas Southall Freeman, the Republican National Convention (1952), and Richmond and Virginia civic affairs.
Also includeed are typed notes and printed materials, 1925-1964, concerning Harry F. Byrd, Sr., with material concerning the campaign against Francis Pickens Miller (1952); and scripts for debates, 1960-1966, with Martin Luther King, Roy Wilkins, Ralph McGill, and William Sloane Coffin
Also included are papers relating to Kilpatrick's activities with the National Council of Editorial Writers and the Virginia Commission on Constitutional Government; and correspondence, 1964-66, concerning speaking and luncheon engagements.
Also included is material relating to his books: tearsheets, editorials, and articles for Interposition (1956); outline, manuscript, correspondence, reviews, and index for The Sovereign States(1957); galleys and reviews for The Lasting South(1957); manuscript, reviews, and correspondence for The Smut Peddlers(1960); and notes, manuscript, editorials, and correspondence for The Southern Case for School Segregation(1962).
Contents List
- Office Files: A-O 1950-1954 (Box 1)
- Office Files: O-Z 1950-1954 (Box 2)
- Office Files: A-E 1953-1954 (Box 3)
- Office Files: F-M 1953-1954 (Box 4)
- Office Files: M-R 1953-1954 (Box 5)
- Office Files: A-Byrd 1955-1957 (Box 7)
- Office Files: Byrd-C 1955-1957 (Box 8)
- Office Files: Cam-Don 1955-1957 (Box 9)
- Office Files: Don-E 1955-1957 (Box 10)
- Office Files: F-Grif 1955-1957 (Box 11)
- Office Files: G-H 1955-1957 (Box 12)
- Office Files: Ham-Hum 1955-1957 (Box 13)
- Office Files: I-Kil 1955-1957 (Box 14)
- Office Files: Kin-L 1955-1957 (Box 15)
- Office Files: Maps-No 1955-1957 (Box 16)
- Office Files: O-Q 1955-1957 (Box 17)
- Office Files: Rio-Rub 1955-1957 (Box 18)
- Office Files: R-Sta 1955-1957 (Box 19)
- Office Files: S-V 1955-1957 (Box 20)
- Office Files: Wal-We 1955-1957 (Box 21)
- Office Files: A-G 1958 (Box 22)
- Office Files: H-N 1958 (Box 23)
- Office Files: N-S 1958 (Box 24)
- Office Files: T-Z 1958 (Box 25)
- Office Files: A-F 1959 (Box 26)
- Office Files: G-M 1959 (Box 27)
- Office Files: N-V 1959 (Box 28)
- Office Files: W-Z 1959 (Box 29)
- Office Files: A-D 1960 (Box 29)
- Office Files: E-K 1960 (Box 30)
- Office Files: L-Q 1960 (Box 31)
- Office Files: R-Z 1960 (Box 32)
- Office Files: A-G 1961 (Box 33)
- Office Files: G-L 1961 (Box 34)
- Office Files: L-O 1961 (Box 35)
- Office Files: P-V 1961 (Box 36)
- Office Files: W-Z 1961 (Box 37)
- Office Files: A-C 1962 (Box 38)
  The remainder of the files for this year have not been transferred to us as yet, but space has been left for them on the shelves.
- Office Files: A-D 1963 (Box 39)
- Office Files: E-M 1963 (Box 40)
- Office Files: N-T 1963 (Box 41)
- Office Files: U-Z 1963 (Box 42)
- Office Files: A-E 1964 (Box 43)
- Office Files: F-L 1964 (Box 44)
- Office Files: M-R 1964 (Box 45)
- Office Files: S-Z 1964 (Box 46)
- Office Files: A-B 1965-1966 (Box 47)
- Office Files: B-C 1965-1966 (Box 48)
- Office Files: C-E 1965-1966 (Box 49)
- Office Files: F-G 1965-1966 (Box 50)
- Office Files: H-I 1965-1966 (Box 51)
- Office Files: J-L 1965-1966 (Box 52)
- Office Files: M 1965-1966 (Box 53)
- Office Files: N-P 1965-1966 (Box 54)
- Office Files: Q-R 1965-1966 (Box 55)
- Office Files: S-T 1965-1966 (Box 56)
- Office Files: U-Z 1965-1966 (Box 57)
- Miscellaneous 1950-1953 (Box 58)
- National Council of Editorial Writers (Box 59-60)
- Interposition letters 1955 (Box 61)
- Speeches, Articles, T.V. Debates, and Appearances (Box 62-64)
- Margaret Wagner File (Box 65)
- The Sovereign States
  - Outline, Manuscript, Correspondence (Box 66)
  - Reviews and Index (Box 67)
- The Smut Peddlers
  - Manuscript, Reviews, Correspondence (Box 68)
  - Manuscript (Box 69)
- The Lasting South
  - Galleys and Reviews (Box 69)
- The Southern Case
  - Notes and Manuscript (Box 70)
  - Editorials, Correspondence, and Manuscript (Box 71)